I would argue that the most important
unanswered question at least in
evolutionary biology has to do with
where the power of evolution comes from
there's the story that we teach about
random mutations being mostly bad
occasionally good the good ones get
favored by selection they accumulate and
that's what makes our forms so effective
that story is true but not very
compelling it's not a lot of power to it
the fact that most mutations are bad and
the occasional one is somewhat good does
not come anywhere close to explaining
how a shrew like animal becomes a
bat-like animal by having membranes and
bones extended in its hands that become
wings there's a flaw in the story that
surrounds the question of how do
mutations alter the morphology of one
creature so that it can take on a
different ecological role my answer to
this would involve something called
Explorer modes Explorer modes are
mechanisms through which an evolved
clade that is a set of creatures
explores design space so that can
discover opportunities that it would not
find by accident if you think about a
creature let's say the most recent
common ancestor of all living mammals
that creature was two things at once one
it was a creature that had an ecology it
found food sufficient to do its
metabolic work and it had a set of
behaviors that allowed it to avoid its
predators whatever they may have been
but at the same time it was also a
creature with the evolutionary potential
to become giraffes and bats and monkeys
and whales and all the other things in
the mammalian clay if you were looking
at that creature you wouldn't
necessarily know that it had all of that
potential you would know only that it
was capable of doing the things that it
did on a daily basis but the fact that
it had
all of that potential means that it's
descendants are still on earth today in
many different forms in fact more than
4000 of them how is it that selection
discovered that from that ancestor you
could make a flying animal a fully
aquatic animal that you could make
animals that never come to the ground
from the treetops how is it that all of
those different modes of being were
discovered and my argument would be
there has to be a mechanism through
which selection finds new opportunities
that are nearby to what the creature in
question is doing but not on a path that
would be discovered by accident now that
may sound far-fetched to people who
believe in a classical version of
evolutionary dynamics but I don't think
it's far-fetched at all because to the
extent that there was exploration that
took place from the perspective of one
creature it would have a high cost but
that exploration would occasionally
return an opportunity or a set of
opportunities that was vast compared to
what a creature exploring haphazardly
would find over time those discoveries
would reinforce let's take an example we
have a small number of species of salmon
in the Pacific they inhabit thousands of
different watersheds some of them very
large like the Columbia River some of
them very tiny barely more than
trickling creeks in order to get a tiny
number of species to find all of those
different opportunities you have two
opportunities one is you could have
random search that is the occasional
accident would result in the fish
swimming into a watershed that it was
not born in and finding a mate and
producing offspring or you could have
exploration of adjacent watersheds in
which creatures that exist in one
watershed have some chance of finding
the next watershed over and checking to
see whether there's an opportunity in it
clearly the second mode finds all of the
empty water fits much faster than an act
battle mode therefore when we look at
the actual behavior of salmon and we see
the small number of individuals do not
return to the stream where they were
born instead of saying this is an
accident what we ought to say is that
this is a high expected value gamble
that is to say creatures that go back to
a watershed that is unfamiliar to them
who have very high likelihood of death
but if they do not die if they discover
a watershed that let's say never had
salmon in it or has had its salmon
population driven extinct by a mudslide
or something else that animal may
out-compete its fellows that went back
to the watershed in which they were born
by many orders of magnitude the creature
that makes the so called
error has an advantage because it may
end up producing a thousand surviving
offspring where its companions in its
home watershed produce on average two
surviving offspring to credit this to
accident is to misunderstand the
calculus high-risk high-reward
activities are often viable even though
if we monitor the average individual
that makes that choice they appear to be
near suicidal so it stands to reason
them that selection would discover
mechanism that searched design space
rather than finding opportunities in
design space haphazardly and if we think
about what we are clearly this is the
case we have a creative capacity that
can search for opportunities that are
nearby hypothesize about how they might
be exploited and then test those
hypotheses and refine some answer we got
that cognitive capacity through
evolutionary dynamics in other words we
were favored to become conscious because
consciousness has an advantage and that
advantage is that it allows us to
discover opportunities that would
otherwise be missed why is it that we
assume we are the only creatures that do
or the consciousness is the only
mechanism that can do this clearly there
are ways that one can test the waters
surrounding an established design to see
if there might be a better design or an
alternative design near
in the case of something like a salmon
it makes no sense to imagine that
they're sitting around in the stream
deliberating how they might deal with
all the alternatives that they've never
seen but it also does make sense that
they would accumulate a tendency to
behave in ways that would discover big
opportunities when they existed nearby
one such way is to gamble under some
circumstances in not going back to the
stream in which you were born in which
case the likelihood of producing no
offspring would certainly be high but
the likelihood of producing a hundred
surviving offspring would be higher than
if you go back to the stream you were
born in and have to compete with all of
the other creatures who did the same
thing so the point I'm trying to make is
that there is certainly a force that
favors rational exploration in design
that force will be reinforced over time
because it will be a jumpring force from
an opportunity that is known to an
opportunity that is unknown and that
jump in force has to be involved in how
it is that the biota
finds all of the remarkably different
ways of existing that we know it to have
found that is a much more powerful
explanation than mutations happen most
of them are bad and occasionally a good
one occurs it will be favored by
selection that answer is simply not
powerful enough to account for the vast
array of niches that have been
discovered by species over the history
of life the question is what are those
mechanisms I would argue consciousness
clearly is one it's one that we can
understand because we wield this but if
we look out on the biota and we stop
telling the story of our random mutation
being the root of all progress what will
be fine what would we discover if we
thought well exploration must be out
there what are the mechanisms through
which it takes place hey folks if you
like this video click like subscribe to
the channel and if you feel like
supporting the creation of more content
like this head on over to my patreon
page and sign up at whatever level feels
comfortable